<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Tableau on Silas Bergen</title>
    <link>http://driftlessdata.space/tags/tableau/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Tableau on Silas Bergen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2017 Silas Bergen</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 14 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://driftlessdata.space/tags/tableau/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Data visualization: Principles and Practice with Tableau Public and Python</title>
      <link>http://driftlessdata.space/project/icots-workshop/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://driftlessdata.space/project/icots-workshop/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Web scraping and data visualization with Python and Tableau</title>
      <link>http://driftlessdata.space/project/uscots2017-workshop/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://driftlessdata.space/project/uscots2017-workshop/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quantifying thrill</title>
      <link>http://driftlessdata.space/post/viz-worldseries-wpa/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Oct 2017 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://driftlessdata.space/post/viz-worldseries-wpa/</guid>
      <description>Monday morning, October 30, found me groggy and sandy-eyed. The culprit was the 5-hour and 17-minute, 10-inning thriller between the LA Dodgers and Houston Astros in Game 5 of the 2017 the night before. Thanks to living in the Central Time Zone, I went to bed around 1am. The Astros ended up defeating the Dodgers 13-12, but the game was insane, featuring three comebacks from deficits of 3 runs or more.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Racial disparity in Winona Area Public School District</title>
      <link>http://driftlessdata.space/post/viz-waps-disparity/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Dec 2016 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://driftlessdata.space/post/viz-waps-disparity/</guid>
      <description>This visualization project was inspired by the excellent This American Life episode,  Is This Working?   The entire episode is well worth a listen, but the gist of the episode was that racial inequity in disciplinary action translates into racial inequity in academic outcomes. I was curious to see if this association held up, in the Winona Area Public Schools, using publicly available data from the Minnesota Department of Education Data Center.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>#OscarsSoWhite</title>
      <link>http://driftlessdata.space/post/viz-oscars/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Feb 2016 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://driftlessdata.space/post/viz-oscars/</guid>
      <description>As I was watching Chris Rock host the 2016 Oscars, I decided to finally scratch my curiosity itch and learn R&amp;rsquo;s Twitter API, twitteR. The 2016 Oscars were controversial, due to the fact that all the actors and actresses nominated were white for the second year in a row. Chris Rock made sure to point this out in his opening monologue, and tweets began using the hashtag #OscarsSoWhite to advance the conversation.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>