<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Silas Bergen</title>
    <link>http://driftlessdata.space/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Silas Bergen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2017 Silas Bergen</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 -0600</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://driftlessdata.space/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>A word in favor of summarytools</title>
      <link>http://driftlessdata.space/post/summarytools/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://driftlessdata.space/post/summarytools/</guid>
      <description>Yesterday, I was preparing material for STAT 405 (biostatistics) I am teaching this spring, and was on the prowl for something that is an improvement upon the base R summary() function (it doesn’t even give standard deviations!). The ideal package would also improve upon the base R table() method, for which getting row and/or column percents is a huge pain. Base function xtabs() is great for getting arrays of contigency tables, but no percents.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Stat consulting: a data science playground</title>
      <link>http://driftlessdata.space/post/dsci-consulting/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://driftlessdata.space/post/dsci-consulting/</guid>
      <description>This past semester I taught our STAT 370 (statistical consulting and communication) for the first time. This course gave student experience consulting for real clients from the university and community and focused on communicating with a client as well as report and presentation preparation best practices. Most of the required analyses were simple: paired t-tests, simple linear regression, etc. What struck me was the nontrivality of the data tidying process! While STAT 370 is taken mostly by our statistics majors, so many of the examples we encountered would be beautiful case studies for our introductory DSCI (data science) curriculum.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data vizzing in Japan</title>
      <link>http://driftlessdata.space/post/icots/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Jul 2018 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://driftlessdata.space/post/icots/</guid>
      <description>This July, my colleage Todd Iverson and I had the incredible opportunity to lead a pre-conference workshop at ICOTS 10 in Kyoto, Japan. Our workshop was titled Data visualization: best practices and principles using Tableau Public and Python.
Our workshop began by covering Leland Wilkinson&amp;rsquo;s grammar of graphics. Most data visualization software (Tableau, Python, R, JMP) employ some version of this grammar, and with a firm understanding it becomes easy to transition between them.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Modeling the Vitruvian Man</title>
      <link>http://driftlessdata.space/post/vitruvian/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://driftlessdata.space/post/vitruvian/</guid>
      <description>This post describes an activity I developed for Stat 310: Intermediate Statistics. This course is the second course on statistics at Winona State. I like to think of it as our “introduction to modeling” course, and this activity does just that: introduces students to the idea of a statistical model, including model assessment and fitting. The activity actually comes in two parts, administered at different times in the semester. In the first part, I am trying to get students to think about how to assess and compare proposed models using residuals.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Public data resources with social justice applications</title>
      <link>http://driftlessdata.space/post/about-social-justice/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Mar 2018 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://driftlessdata.space/post/about-social-justice/</guid>
      <description>Yesterday, several students and I traveled to St. Olaf to illustrate several uses of interesting, publicly-available data that can be used to investigate &amp;ldquo;social justice&amp;rdquo; issues. I&amp;rsquo;ve long been meaning to compile all the data sources and some example projects I&amp;rsquo;ve developed over the years, and this talk provided just the right motivation. Accordingly, I have compiled a list of some of my favorite data sources and example projects and student work.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data set gold mine</title>
      <link>http://driftlessdata.space/post/ufl/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://driftlessdata.space/post/ufl/</guid>
      <description>Quick one here. As a statistics educator I am always on the lookout for interesting, real, digestable data that illustrate important statistical concepts. That’s a tall order!
One site that I visit again and again is this excellent repository hosted at University of Florida. Here’s the link. I regularly ping this website for classes ranging from intro stats to experimental design to regression analysis. Not only are they varied in scope and organized by topic, they also have brief descriptions and citations of original sources.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Notes from Liberal Arts Data Science Workshop</title>
      <link>http://driftlessdata.space/post/lads/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Jan 2018 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://driftlessdata.space/post/lads/</guid>
      <description>When temperatures hit 0&amp;deg;F in Minnesota, what better remedy than to head to Florida and talk data science curriculum! The 2-day workshop was held at the New College of Florida in Sarasota, FL. This post reflects some of the ideas circulated at the workshop that stood out to me.
Multivariate thinking and the introductory statistics and data science course: preparing students to make sense of a world of observational data (Nick Horton) In this talk, Dr.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What students have to say about group homework</title>
      <link>http://driftlessdata.space/post/group-homework/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://driftlessdata.space/post/group-homework/</guid>
      <description>The past two semesters of teaching our lower-level introductory statistics course here at WSU, I’ve incorporated in-class group homework. I could go on at length about why *I* think group homework is beneficial, but that’s not the point of this post. Rather, this is about what the students think. I think it’s quite striking!
First, though, I do need to provide a couple quick details about how I manage group homework.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On elementary perceptual tasks</title>
      <link>http://driftlessdata.space/post/on-epts/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://driftlessdata.space/post/on-epts/</guid>
      <description>One of the first concepts I talk about in my data visualization course is the idea of the elementary perceptual task (EPT), an idea explored in depth by visualization pioneers William S. Cleveland and Robert McGill. Essentially, EPTs are visual building blocks for comparing quantities. The EPTs are summarized nicely in Figure 1 from Graphical Perception: Theory, Experiementation, and Application to the Development of Graphical Methods:
For example, looking at the two dots in the upper-left pane, we perceive that the top dot represents a larger quantity than the bottom dot, because it is higher on a common scale than the bottom dot.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Gestalt principles and income inequality</title>
      <link>http://driftlessdata.space/post/income-gestalt/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://driftlessdata.space/post/income-gestalt/</guid>
      <description>The fall semester is over and final grades are in, which means it’s time to reflect on what just took place and how to grow from here. Today, I reflect on my third time teaching the data visualization course. This course has come a long way since the first time I taught it in Fall 2015, and yet there are still so many improvements to make! One of the concepts I want to greater emphasize next time I teach the course are the Gestalt principles, which Gestalt psychologist Kurt Koffka summarizes as the idea that “The whole is other than the sum of the parts.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>And the winner is...</title>
      <link>http://driftlessdata.space/post/policedatachallenge/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Dec 2017 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://driftlessdata.space/post/policedatachallenge/</guid>
      <description>The midterm project for my data visualization course this past fall required students to submit to the ASA&amp;rsquo;s Police Data Challenge. The competition involved analyzing millions of 911 calls for one of three cities (Baltimore, Cincinnati, or Seattle). I had the students investigate the Seattle data set, since it contained latitudes and longitudes of each call.
Several weeks later, we received the exciting news that one of the teams won &amp;ldquo;Best Overall&amp;rdquo; among undergraduate teams!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Minne MUDAC 2017</title>
      <link>http://driftlessdata.space/post/minnemudac/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Nov 2017 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://driftlessdata.space/post/minnemudac/</guid>
      <description>Winona State University undergraduates made a great impression at the 2017 MinneMUDAC data analytics competition    
On November 3-4, Winona State statistics and data science students participated in the fantastic MinneMUDAC 2017 data analytics competition. Students worked in teams of up to five students for one month analyzing de-identified administrative medical and pharmacy claims data provided by Optum. The competition required students to analyze complicated data on health insurance claims made by Type-II diabetics.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quantifying thrill</title>
      <link>http://driftlessdata.space/post/viz-worldseries-wpa/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Oct 2017 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://driftlessdata.space/post/viz-worldseries-wpa/</guid>
      <description>Monday morning, October 30, found me groggy and sandy-eyed. The culprit was the 5-hour and 17-minute, 10-inning thriller between the LA Dodgers and Houston Astros in Game 5 of the 2017 the night before. Thanks to living in the Central Time Zone, I went to bed around 1am. The Astros ended up defeating the Dodgers 13-12, but the game was insane, featuring three comebacks from deficits of 3 runs or more.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A summer REU at Winona State</title>
      <link>http://driftlessdata.space/post/winstats/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Sep 2017 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://driftlessdata.space/post/winstats/</guid>
      <description>This past summer, I along with my colleagues Chris Malone and Brant Deppa had the fantastic opportunity to host four students for a 10-week summer research experience for undergraduates (REU). Winona State was awarded the REU by the American Statistical Association, which had received a grant from the NSF to fund four students at each of nine sites over the course of three years (three different sites per year).
Megan Aadland (South Dakota State), Jenn Halbleib (Amherst), Adrianna Kallis (Iowa State), and Eva Tourangeau (Lawrence) were selected from a competitive, national pool of undergraduates.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Racial disparity in Winona Area Public School District</title>
      <link>http://driftlessdata.space/post/viz-waps-disparity/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Dec 2016 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://driftlessdata.space/post/viz-waps-disparity/</guid>
      <description>This visualization project was inspired by the excellent This American Life episode,  Is This Working?   The entire episode is well worth a listen, but the gist of the episode was that racial inequity in disciplinary action translates into racial inequity in academic outcomes. I was curious to see if this association held up, in the Winona Area Public Schools, using publicly available data from the Minnesota Department of Education Data Center.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>#OscarsSoWhite</title>
      <link>http://driftlessdata.space/post/viz-oscars/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Feb 2016 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://driftlessdata.space/post/viz-oscars/</guid>
      <description>As I was watching Chris Rock host the 2016 Oscars, I decided to finally scratch my curiosity itch and learn R&amp;rsquo;s Twitter API, twitteR. The 2016 Oscars were controversial, due to the fact that all the actors and actresses nominated were white for the second year in a row. Chris Rock made sure to point this out in his opening monologue, and tweets began using the hashtag #OscarsSoWhite to advance the conversation.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>