<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Students on Silas Bergen</title>
    <link>http://driftlessdata.space/tags/students/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Students on Silas Bergen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2017 Silas Bergen</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 23 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://driftlessdata.space/tags/students/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Modeling the Vitruvian Man</title>
      <link>http://driftlessdata.space/post/vitruvian/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://driftlessdata.space/post/vitruvian/</guid>
      <description>This post describes an activity I developed for Stat 310: Intermediate Statistics. This course is the second course on statistics at Winona State. I like to think of it as our “introduction to modeling” course, and this activity does just that: introduces students to the idea of a statistical model, including model assessment and fitting. The activity actually comes in two parts, administered at different times in the semester. In the first part, I am trying to get students to think about how to assess and compare proposed models using residuals.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What students have to say about group homework</title>
      <link>http://driftlessdata.space/post/group-homework/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://driftlessdata.space/post/group-homework/</guid>
      <description>The past two semesters of teaching our lower-level introductory statistics course here at WSU, I’ve incorporated in-class group homework. I could go on at length about why *I* think group homework is beneficial, but that’s not the point of this post. Rather, this is about what the students think. I think it’s quite striking!
First, though, I do need to provide a couple quick details about how I manage group homework.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>And the winner is...</title>
      <link>http://driftlessdata.space/post/policedatachallenge/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Dec 2017 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://driftlessdata.space/post/policedatachallenge/</guid>
      <description>The midterm project for my data visualization course this past fall required students to submit to the ASA&amp;rsquo;s Police Data Challenge. The competition involved analyzing millions of 911 calls for one of three cities (Baltimore, Cincinnati, or Seattle). I had the students investigate the Seattle data set, since it contained latitudes and longitudes of each call.
Several weeks later, we received the exciting news that one of the teams won &amp;ldquo;Best Overall&amp;rdquo; among undergraduate teams!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Minne MUDAC 2017</title>
      <link>http://driftlessdata.space/post/minnemudac/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Nov 2017 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://driftlessdata.space/post/minnemudac/</guid>
      <description>Winona State University undergraduates made a great impression at the 2017 MinneMUDAC data analytics competition    
On November 3-4, Winona State statistics and data science students participated in the fantastic MinneMUDAC 2017 data analytics competition. Students worked in teams of up to five students for one month analyzing de-identified administrative medical and pharmacy claims data provided by Optum. The competition required students to analyze complicated data on health insurance claims made by Type-II diabetics.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A summer REU at Winona State</title>
      <link>http://driftlessdata.space/post/winstats/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Sep 2017 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://driftlessdata.space/post/winstats/</guid>
      <description>This past summer, I along with my colleagues Chris Malone and Brant Deppa had the fantastic opportunity to host four students for a 10-week summer research experience for undergraduates (REU). Winona State was awarded the REU by the American Statistical Association, which had received a grant from the NSF to fund four students at each of nine sites over the course of three years (three different sites per year).
Megan Aadland (South Dakota State), Jenn Halbleib (Amherst), Adrianna Kallis (Iowa State), and Eva Tourangeau (Lawrence) were selected from a competitive, national pool of undergraduates.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>