<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>R on Silas Bergen</title>
    <link>http://driftlessdata.space/tags/r/</link>
    <description>Recent content in R on Silas Bergen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2017 Silas Bergen</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 02 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://driftlessdata.space/tags/r/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Stat consulting: a data science playground</title>
      <link>http://driftlessdata.space/post/dsci-consulting/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://driftlessdata.space/post/dsci-consulting/</guid>
      <description>This past semester I taught our STAT 370 (statistical consulting and communication) for the first time. This course gave student experience consulting for real clients from the university and community and focused on communicating with a client as well as report and presentation preparation best practices. Most of the required analyses were simple: paired t-tests, simple linear regression, etc. What struck me was the nontrivality of the data tidying process! While STAT 370 is taken mostly by our statistics majors, so many of the examples we encountered would be beautiful case studies for our introductory DSCI (data science) curriculum.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Stat consulting: a data science playground</title>
      <link>http://driftlessdata.space/post/dsci-consulting.utf8/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://driftlessdata.space/post/dsci-consulting.utf8/</guid>
      <description>This past semester I taught our STAT 370 (statistical consulting and communication) for the first time. This course gave student experience consulting for real clients from the university and community and focused on communicating with a client as well as report and presentation preparation best practices. Most of the required analyses were simple: paired t-tests, simple linear regression, etc. What struck me was the nontrivality of the data tidying process!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quantifying thrill</title>
      <link>http://driftlessdata.space/post/viz-worldseries-wpa/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Oct 2017 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://driftlessdata.space/post/viz-worldseries-wpa/</guid>
      <description>Monday morning, October 30, found me groggy and sandy-eyed. The culprit was the 5-hour and 17-minute, 10-inning thriller between the LA Dodgers and Houston Astros in Game 5 of the 2017 the night before. Thanks to living in the Central Time Zone, I went to bed around 1am. The Astros ended up defeating the Dodgers 13-12, but the game was insane, featuring three comebacks from deficits of 3 runs or more.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>#OscarsSoWhite</title>
      <link>http://driftlessdata.space/post/viz-oscars/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Feb 2016 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://driftlessdata.space/post/viz-oscars/</guid>
      <description>As I was watching Chris Rock host the 2016 Oscars, I decided to finally scratch my curiosity itch and learn R&amp;rsquo;s Twitter API, twitteR. The 2016 Oscars were controversial, due to the fact that all the actors and actresses nominated were white for the second year in a row. Chris Rock made sure to point this out in his opening monologue, and tweets began using the hashtag #OscarsSoWhite to advance the conversation.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>